it may seem odd to study
thinkers who wrote over 2000 years ago.
We don t study scientists from ancient
times, and we don't treat what they
thought as anything more than historical curiosity.
So why do philosophy courses spend so
much time on ancient greek philosophers?
There are two reasons why greek philosophy
is still relevant to us to day.
One is the nature of philosophy itself.
Philosophy deals with the biggest and
most complex issues facing humanity, and
philosophical insights underpin all human endeavors.
Because the questions considered by philosophy are
so large and complicated, philosophy itself is
a long conversation about those issues among
many people across many years.
Philosophers understand that philosophers of the
past, even the distant past, are
valuable resources for us today.
To compare past perspectives with our
own perspectives today helps us better
understand the questions we consider.
The second reason we still study ancient greek
philosophy is that the thinkers of greek philosophy
laid down the foundation of not just philosophy,
but all of western civilization.
There have been many influences throughout
history on who we are today.
But what greek philosophers wrote over 2000 years
ago contributed a surprising amount to everything that
has happened in the west since.
We know of several dozen philosophers from
ancient Greece, and covering them all can
easily fill whole books and university courses.
Two ancient Greeks stand out as significantly more
influential than the others, Plato and Aristotle.
For the past 2300 years, Plato and Aristotle
have been pillars of the western world.
Their two worldviews have often been in competition with
each other, but people, recognizing their significance, have tried
to blend their ideas as best they could.
The worldviews of Plato and Aristotle at
first seem foreign to us today.
But if you look more closely, you can see threads in
each of their philosophies that are woven into our social fabric
and to understand who we are, how we got here, and
how we can approach the problems we face today.
Those are the reasons we
study ancient greek philosophy today.